HUANG XIE Doctoral Researcher

6+ years in developing machine learning models for audio signal processing, natural language processing, and information retrieval, and 10+ years in software development. Proficiency in machine learning, audio/text processing, data analysis, web development, and Python & Java programming.



Personal Info

- Huang Xie
- huang.xie@outlook.com
- +358 40 3219383
- Tampere, Finland
- github.com/xieh97
- in linkedin.com/in/huang-xie-28b7872bb
- orcid.org/0000-0001-7609-8049

Languages

Chinese English Finnish Native Professional Beginner

Referees

Prof. Tuomas Virtanen

- ② Tampere University
- tuomas.virtanen@tuni.fi

Assoc. Prof. Okko Räsänen

- Tampere University
- okko.rasanen@tuni.fi

Employment

Doctoral Researcher | Research Assistant

03/2019 - Present

- Audio Research Group, Tampere University, Finland
 - Developed machine learning models (e.g., CNNs, RNNs, transformers) for multimodal learning, audio signal processing, natural language processing, and information retrieval.
 - Collected, analyzed, and processed large audio and text datasets (e.g., feature extraction, semantic analysis, classification, clustering).
 - Published 9+ first-authored scientific papers in prestigious journals and conferences (e.g., IEEE/ACM TASLP, SPL, ICASSP).

Software Engineer

10/2015 - 05/2018

- **♀** Bohai Commodity Exchange, Tianjin, China
 - Developed key features for CloudBoce (%, an E-Commerce platform), including shopping cart, order processing, and product management.
 - Collaborated with cross-functional teams (e.g., UI designers, product managers) to define, design, and ship new features.
 - Troubleshot and debugged issues related to performance, crashes, and other bugs, ensuring smooth and stable user experience.

Principal Java Developer

07/2014 - 09/2015

09/2010 - 06/2014

- Qingdao Industrial Software Research Institute, Qingdao, China
 - Led the development and delivery of multiple enterprise-grade software solutions (e.g., BPM, CMS), overseeing the full project lifecycle from planning to deployment.
 - Mentored junior developers and performed code reviews to maintain high coding standards and best practices.
 - Collaborated with cross-functional teams to define requirements, troubleshoot issues, and deliver high-quality software on schedule.
 - Presented technical solutions to non-technical stakeholders, and managed technical documentation and reports.

Skills

Programming: Python, Java, JavaScript, SQL, C/C++, Kotlin **Machine Learning**: PyTorch, Tensorflow, scikit-learn, Ray, Spark

Data Analysis: NumPy, SciPy, Pandas, NLTK, Matplotlib

Web Development: Java EE, Spring, Hibernate, Django, Flask, MySQL, Git

Education

M.Eng. in Software Engineering

PhD in Signal Processing and Machine Learning

O1/2021 - Present

Tampere University, Tampere, Finland

M.Sc. in Data Engineering and Machine Learning

Tampere University, Tampere, Finland

O8/2018 - 11/2020

Q University of Science and Technology of China, Hefei, China

Activities

- ₱ Reviewer for IEEE/ACM TASLP, SPL, ICASSP, WASPAA, DCASE, etc.
- Task coordinator for Language-based Audio Retrieval and Automated Audio Captioning in DCASE Challenge 2022 (%), 2023 (%), and 2024 (%).

